Next we're going to go to processes and
services then or services and
processes really.  So in
services and processes,
let's see, here it is.  Okay, the other
day we were, uh, we
were working on the concept,
we're a bit between the topics of
multiprocess programming and
multithreading programming and we were left with him
commenting that today we were going to look at the topic,
although we start today and continue the
next day, of parallel and
distributed computing.  Okay?  For this,
we are going to look at Socket Client and Socket
Server.  Let's talk about
distributed communication across a network.  Okay,
let's go to new file 002
uh, well, 003, I think.  003 eh
workers.html.
[Music]
Okay, so for that we're going to explore that in
HTML,
in JavaScript, to be more precise, there's the
figure of the worker.  The worker figure
is basically a thread, a
processing thread within which between
us and the machine, it is clear that
we have the web browser in between, and
the web browser in between, well, it is not
a software specifically designed to
be, okay?, specifically designed to
be efficient in terms of
resource use, but hey, something is something, right?
So let's see, uh, JS worker
minimal example,
okay?  So there's a method
called new worker.  Wait, let's
see.  Yes, okay.  Okay.  Okay, this is the
worker, okay?  There's a, here it is, there's a
worker that's a new worker, that is, it
's a default
JavaScript object, in fact, for a
few years now.  The thing is, it goes
very unnoticed, okay?  And here and here
I'm going to create a js worker.   I
'm going to call it worker 3 or 003 worker
because since we're going to create multiple
versions of this file, it's fine.
003worker.cs.js.
Good.  Now I'm going over here, I'm going to
local host,
I'm going to
I'm going to second, I'm going to services and
multithreaded processes.  Uh, no, sorry.  Oh,
wait.  Yes, just a moment.  Where am I?
Distributed pair.  Exercises.  Okay.  And
HTML workers.  Very good.  It is important that
this has to be done on a
local server, on a patch, okay?  It cannot be
said directly.  Start worker
momentin and count 1. Okay?  Good.  What's going
on?
So what's happening, let's look at
the code, is that here in the worker,
here in the worker,
what I have is a set interval, a set
interval that has one second, okay?  That
is, it has one second of time,
which means that E data is
equal to start.  No, I don't need it.
Let's see it.  No, we're going to
do the simplest example we
can ever make of a
worker.  Worker post message, no good.
Stop on click.  No, no, no, no.  I don't
need this.
on message.  Okay.  Okay.  Very good.
And now next in the worker, I'm
simply going to say post message is
that what you were seeing is not the
most representative sample.  Okay,
then let's see.
Hey, worker post message, hello.  from the
main thread to the worker
and the worker wave from the worker back
to the main thread.  So you can see that the
interface for sending and receiving
information is actually very simple.
First it is an instant worker, second
when I receive a message and third I
send you a message.  Okay?  This is the
return channel
and this is the outward channel.
Okay, let's see.  Let's see.  Now
the example is simplified.
Okay, and web worker demo.  It's not that this is
not necessary and this is not necessary.
Okay, so you don't think it's
difficult, okay?  Okay.  Hey, that gives us
a click.  I don't want a click anymore.
Oh, okay.  Okay.  It was a click away.  Wow,
that's it.  What do you think?
Okay, GPT chat does this with all the best
intentions in the world, but there are
times when you say, "It could be
simpler than that."  Okay.  Okay.  Hello
from the worker back to the
main thread.  That is, a
message has been sent, the worker has picked up the message,
and the worker has returned.  Okay,
but next, next I'm going
to say I'm going to say uh console.log
with console.log
uh and data.
Okay.
Okay.  Hello back.  Hello from the
worker.  Back to the main hero.
Once we've done this, once
I've made it clear that the
workers' interface is clear, it
couldn't be clearer, okay?  More intuitive,
easier, that is, create a worker, send
messages, listen to messages, that's it.
Okay, now here comes the
fun part.  004, strong calculation.
004. I'm going to 004 worker,
right?  004 worker.
Okay.  Okay.  I go to the 004 worker
and I tell him and I tell him the 004 worker is going to
say the classic.
For let i equals 0. I is less than
unchuunchu
and more than.  and I say,
uh, LED number is equal to 1.00 and a
decimal, so the classic example of
forcing a heavy calculation.  And I say number
multiplied equals 1.00.
Okay?  Okay.  So,
next,
next strong calculation, okay?  And
sorry and I come here and I will see that there is
a core
that is there.  Hit me.
Okay, I'll see a core that's there, hit it
.  If you want, if you want what I
could have done is here at the end
of the worker,
post message
finished.
Okay, I can't do it now.  I'm going to start
another one.
Okay,
okay.  Now I will have torn out
another core.   My
processor is starting to make itself heard.
Okay.  And now, at some point I may have
put a very heavy calculation on it, I don't know.
Probably.  Okay.  Hey, let's see.
Come on.  Since I have put a heavy calculation on it
.  Yes, wait.  There.  Okay, so
that's
it.  Okay, now I've gone a
little too far.
Come on.  And finished more.
And finished a little more.  No more.
Okay.  And now take about 10 seconds,
okay?  And finished.
But of course, what happens?  So
what I can do next is
create an array of workers,
okay?  So 005 array of workers.  And
so if a
heavy-duty worker is already easy,
creating an array of workers is going to be
even easier because LED workers
equals array.
And then I say
let number workers
equals 8, for example.
We'll talk about it now.  So I say
for
let i
is equal to 0
and is less than number workers
and plus more
and then I say workers of i
is equal to new worker.  So,
I'm not creating one worker, I'm creating
eight workers.  Okay?  So, now
here,
now here.  That's not exactly
clean, but it's okay.
Workers day.  I give each one a
listener
and each one a sender.
And then now And then now
And then now eh I think I haven't
derived it to the five five worker.  Okay,
so now
I enter the workers ray.  Eh, worker is
not define.  Where?  Ah, here.  Workers.   There
.  Okay, surcharge.  Okay, I'm going, I'm going
to the monitor and look at what's happening on the
monitor.
And this is what it is, okay?  And I am and I
am They are already coming, they are already
coming.  Do you see it?  Aside from that, the
interface for when they arrive is
super expensive because since you have it in the
JavaScript console, it
arrives to you.  So what happens?  Well,
if this subject is about
multi-processing,
damn it, well, JavaScript and the
web browser serve as a
multi-core computing platform.  Who would have
told you?  I mean, it sounds
weird, but it is like that.
If I want to find out the number of
cores I have in the machine,
okay?  And now next I say 006, the
number of cores
on my machine.
And I turn this into 006 worker,
okay?  Well, the number of cores, LED
number of cores
is equal to navigator punh hardware
concurrency.   That
is, it is a, that is, the web browser
has a parameter that is hardware
concurrency, so I don't have
to do eight.  I can say, adapt to the
number of cores this
machine has.  So I'm going to 006.
We're going to 006.
Wait, tell me.
Console.log
number of workers or number of cores, it doesn't
matter to me.
Ok, 006 and it tells me 16. It
correctly detects the cores of my
machine
and puts the machine at full speed.
And it's super easy.  And now they're
finishing up and they're arriving and they're doing
whatever, okay?
And as I say, if you notice, the way
of sending and the way, that is, we can
use multicore and I don't have to use
all the cores because as you
can see, OBS is recording my
zoom.  Luis, Luis, I've already figured out
why when I teach this
everyone says it, okay?  The evil idea of
multi-core is in the browser, because of
course, I
'm obviously in my local browser right now, but I
could serve this on a web page to the
internet, to the world.  Okay?  I know
you are having an evil idea
about using
remote users' resources for evil.  Yes I
know.  Okay, I know, I know.  Luis, you
're thinking about this because every time
I teach this to everyone, it
occurs to them
and I don't say no.  Okay, just a moment, just a
moment.  You see, uh, I'm going to tell you
something because now next,
of course, this was on a
local computer, okay?  But remember, this
is
parallel and distributed computing, right?  But?
FB your door lock.  Well, you know
what happens?  If you lived in the United States,
you'd have a problem, but
in Spain, nothing matters, you know?
Here in Spain, as long as you don't steal from the
State, you can do whatever you want
.  That's why you can do whatever
you want to anyone because the
state doesn't give a damn, you know?  Because the
state is as long as you don't bother me,
kill whoever you want, you know?  But
anyway, if you kill him, don't kill him
too high, but anyway.  Good.  Uh, in the late
90s there was a project called City
at home Home, which is no longer operational,
right?  is no longer available.  But if we
look at the page,
if we look at the page, the initial release
is in 1999,
mind you, that's a lot of merit, right?  And it was
stopped indefinitely on
March 31st.  In '99, there wasn't the
computing power, the number of processors,
distributed servers, right?  But I
was starting to see the internet.
SETI is one of the projects
searching for extraterrestrial intelligence.
The problem that the United States had, in
this case, in the 1990s, is
that sweeping the entire space,
analyzing the entire space is a
huge task, it's an endless task, right?
But SETI came up with it.  Hey, what if
we distributed computing power across all the
people connected to the Internet—
which in '99 started to number in the millions—
and asked people to
donate their computing power to us, okay?  You
apart from when you started the program from the
set home, you opened this, okay?  And you were
amazed because, I mean, they sent you
a packet of information, they
used your computer to analyze that
small packet of information and it was
sent back, and so on with millions of
computers, right?  And you were amazed.  And it's
basically the same thing
you're thinking, but instead of applying
data mining,
uh, which in this case is, well,
a slightly more
individual and selfish, pecuniary,
monetary interest, okay?  But what if we
used it for something that would benefit
all of humanity?  I mean, the whole
seti thing was, well, there's a lot of
space to scan, but on Earth there
are a lot of computers.  What if
we used the Earth as a
giant brain?  Okay?  And among all the
computers we calculate faster.
I think if aliens ever visit us one day
and see projects like
these, they'll say, "Wow, these people are cool."
Know?  These people are, I mean, if they think
like this, they're moving in the
right direction, but of course, then I understand that
there are many other things that we do and
they'll say, well no, they're not moving
in the right direction.  But anyway, so
the idea is this, I mean, I just
told you about seti to tell you
that well, you can make other uses of
distributed computing that aren't
necessarily mining, but to
everyone, I tell you that when I
show this to someone, everyone
thinks about the mining thing.   Of
course, now I'm
going to do a little
demonstration,
which is going to be taking a
data packet and calculating it.  Okay?  Let's see
why now 007
data packet, okay?
Like when we download the pirate, in
what sense?
Data packet.  I say this because I don't
see the parallel right now,
but I'm sure there are several possible ones.
And 007.
Okay, so let's see now and now
comes the topic of communication between
processes, semaphores, all that.  Okay,
now you'll see what a move it is.  So,
let's see.  Just a moment, I have the mic.
Yes, okay, correct.
Now what I'm going to
do next is I'm going to say, eh, LED package
is equal to, I don't know, you know?  Look, I'm going to
GPT chat and I'm going to tell him that
uh
hm Well, you know?  Give me the first paragraph
of this Don Quixote
.  Oh, [ __ ] no.  Okay, uh, no, but
much more so, in its full form.
Let's see.  Oh, okay, yeah, yeah, yeah, correct.
Yes, yes, yes, exactly.  Okay, but no, I
mean, the one on the set home, I'm telling you, was
totally aware.  Uh, you
can use a lot of, let's say, a lot of
things for evil, right?  But the idea
is that there will certainly be other things, other
people thinking about how to use it for
evil, but let's think about how to
use it for good, okay?
So let eh let package
is equal to this, okay?  Okay, and
then LED eh tokens
equals package split of the space.
Good.  And in the meantime,
what I'm going to do, what I'm going to do
is a
very, very far from
Transformers kind of thing, okay?  Very far, very
far, very far, very far.
Console.log log tokens.  What I just
did, what I just did is leave,
okay?  There you split a paragraph into an array
of words that in the context of
artificial intelligence we would call
tokens, right?  They are not just words,
but well, let's take them as
individual words.
From there, of course, what I'm going to
do is
take this, break this into 16 pieces,
okay?  length
equals LED length
equals tokens.  Length
and console.  log
length,
okay?  And 162. Okay, now next I
'm going to say, uh, LED block equals
length
match number of cores.
But console punl log
block will
give me a decimal number.  Hello.  Number of
cores.  Number of Ah, number of
cores.  Okay, okay, sorry.
Okay, 10,125.
Okay, so what I need is the
mat
failing.
Math.  Fail.
Okay, 11. Good.  And from here,
and from here.
Okay.
Okay.  And from here, console.log
block for a second now I want to
split this packet
into each of these blocks, okay?  And
let's see for
a moment, a moment that I'm
thinking,
okay?  for
let
i is ig to 0 and is less than eh
number of cores because the number of
cores is the number of packets that
I have and plus plus and then
LED packets
is equal to array and I say packets pun
push and Now I say e no, wait.  Tokens
dot splice,
okay?  Published
by block comma
block.
And if everything went well, console.  OG
packages.
What I just did
there.  Oh wow, 32. Why 32?
Wait, wait, wait.  Oh,
no, no.
Ah, no, no, no.  Sorry, sorry.  11. What
do you mean 11?  No, let's see.
Okay,
LED copy equals
tokens.
Now copy dot splic.  Now yes.  Okay.
I was loading the original lightning, I
think.  Let's see.  No, no, not yet.
Why is everything here?  Okay, it's all there.   It
should be there to start with because there are
32.
More number of cores.  More
because there are 32.
Let's see
why number of cores.  Ah, maybe it
detects 32 cores.  Don't know.  No, I
shouldn't.  Okay, so copy dot
splices.
Oh, wow.  Uh, wait.  This should
be giving an error.
And block.
This is something else.
In a place in La Mancha whose name I
don't want to remember.  Okay, 16. Why is it
why is it why isn't it going
all the way?  Don't know.  I don't know
right now, but basically this starts to
illustrate the process I want to do,
okay?  Which is basically taking a pack
of tokens and processing them.  Sure, what would you
say I'm going to do now?
Well, as you can imagine, what I'm going to
do now is send each of
these packets to each of the
processing cores.  Hey, I insist, we're
still local, but as you can
imagine, if tomorrow there aren't
eight, but 8,000, and there are 10
connected devices, then I'll send a
packet of 1,000 to each connected device.
Okay, we'll take it step by step, obviously,
but you can imagine what we're
doing with this.
So now next I'd like to
know, well, there are 16 cores now,
thank goodness, although there are going to be 16 there are going to
be eight cores that are dying of laughter,
but okay, I don't know, it doesn't matter what it is.
Let's see.
And by block, okay, well,
whatever.  Okay, now
I unlock the cores,
okay?  And in the post message, and now
comes the question.
In the post message
what I'm going to do is send
tokens, packets, sorry,
I. packets.
And in the worker what I'm going to do
is eh LED data is equal to E.data.
And look, post message data.
Let's see it.   I
remove the console.
And let's see what comes back.
And this is what comes back.
This is what is coming back from
each of the workers.
And now I'm going to do some
simple operation, okay?  For example, let's see,
JavaScript and JS char to appear in
JavaScript, not in CSS, obviously.
Ah, look, there you go.   I
had no control over how easy it would be.
Well for
let i is ig to 0 and is less than data pun
leng
plus
data of i is equal to char to is not
data of i to supercase and post message
data ok and now I come here I
reload and if you notice what I'm
seeing from the workers
is this.  It is the text in capital letters.  It's
a very silly operation, okay?  It's very
silly, but it just goes to
show that if we can do
this, we can do whatever we want
, right?
And
no, look, I'm not imagining Google
doing calculations with a million
powerful computers.   It's
not that I imagine it, it's what it is
, it's how it works.   I
mean, that's been the reality for
years.
The what is not the unknown, the how is the
unknown.  And this exercise is intended to
illustrate how, right?  It comes to
illustrate, of course, what happens?  Well,
over the next few days, we'll continue
doing exercises like
this one to show you that technology
isn't difficult.  Now, what is going to
be difficult for us, I think,
is this part here.   That is
, taking a problem that
is linear, because what you're seeing
is a linear problem, it's a
linear paragraph, and analyzing what strategies
we can use to take a linear problem,
break it down into many problems that
can be solved in parallel,
okay?  For example, uploading videos
to YouTube may be using 1000
servers altogether.  Fran, don't even doubt it.  I
mean, I mean, did you doubt it?
Let's ask it,
but not right now, but rather, uh, for example,
how many servers
on YouTube can be processing
not just the upload, not just the upload,
but also the video compression in a
parallel or distributed manner?  Because of
course, YouTube
doesn't have a parallelism problem, it
has a distribution problem.  That is to
say, YouTube doesn't have a single
giant video to process across thousands of
computers, but rather millions
of people uploading millions of videos,
so by providing a computer
for each person, in quotes, it's already
solved.  But let's see what
Chat GPT tells us.  an estimate.   He
probably doesn't have the exact data,
obviously, but he can certainly
give us an estimate.
Let's see.   There is
no public figure.  It's clear.
This was very clear that it was going to happen,
but for
a moment.
[Music]
Okay,
okay.  The video is encoded in multiple
codexes, effectively in multiple
resolutions.  Okay, how many machines
for a video?
Okay, okay.  Segmented into
2-second chunks and encoded in two codexes, there
are 6 encoding tasks.
Many are grouped by worker.
Note that I haven't said anything
about workers to the GPT chat,
okay?  They are paralyzable units,
tens to scale.  Okay, so let's
see.
Okay, tens of thousands of machines per
work, per cluster, and with multiple clusters
in parallel, meaning millions of
active tasks distributed continuously.
Google does not publish the number of
servers.  Let's see.
H, well,
I'll tell you, right?  I mean, they won't give us a
specific number, but I can tell you that
in the case of Google and the problem of
video segmentation, which
is actually a good example, the truth is, we
could be talking about, I mean,
Google's video segmentation
is a similar case to what we did
last week, which is taking an image,
breaking it into pieces, solving each piece,
okay?  It's the same, but applied to
video.  Take a video, break it into pieces,
send each piece to a
different machine, collect the pieces, and put it back
together.  Of course, picking up the pieces and putting it
back together is part of what we'll be
looking at here, which is interprocess communication
and interprocess synchronization
.  That is to say, it is not acceptable to me that, as we
say today, a worker,
each worker is vomiting their
contents at me and that's it.  And I say, "Yeah,
but I need it all together."  Okay?
So if you want, if you want, what I'm
going to do is the following at the end,
because this isn't of much use to me, they
're throwing up the Okay, right,
correct.  No, no, no.  100 servers and
one video per server.  Well, either yes or
also, you know?  So, 008 eh
recompose
the data.   I
'm going to show you a short
traffic light system, which is a classic in
parallel computing, okay?  And I say,
let's see,
LED traffic light
is equal to 0.
Every time a worker answers me,
traffic light plus more.
And then every time a worker
responds to me, if semaphore
equals, I think number of cores
if semaphore equals number of
cores.  Console.
we're done.
And if we're done,
that means
we're done, right?  Note that we have
finished and it does not appear until
all the data returns.  That means
console.  log.  Now we recompose the
data
and I'm going to say LED recompose
equals Ray,
okay?  And then I say, let's compose
quietly.
There we
recompose from IG
to e pun data.
No, sorry.
Well, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.  AE.  Data.  And
at the end console.  we
recompose log.
Let's see it.  And in the end we have an
array in a but we already have an array,
okay?  We don't have a bunch of
different chuns, we have one result.  And if you
want
And if you want eh LED string is equal to
nothing,
for let J
is equal to 0.
J is less than that
we recompose.
point length
J+
and then chain more equal to
we recompose.
No, wait
a moment, just a moment.
Okay, LED J.
Okay.  And now LED JK.
Now yes.  Okay, one
more chain equals
slaps, wait.  Ah, we're recomposing from
J, I
think.  Hey, I'm not with anyone else right now
.  We recompose from J and K.
Surely there is an easier way to
square a chain, but oh well.  Console.
Log string.
Oh, K k.
This is the K. This is the K and this is the
K.
Okay.
And no console dot log string.
Hello.  Coma.  Chain.
No. Ah, ah, sorry.  More equal, more
equal, more equal.
No.
Oh, gosh, I can't redefine.  Goes.
Oh, you got it.  Oh yeah, sorry.  And
more space, sorry.
And there you have it.
In a place in La Mancha whose name I do
not want to be mentioned.  I
think that's not right, huh?  I think
somewhere in La Mancha.
Ah, from spear to shipyard instead of the
stain.  Well, I'll have to see about that.  I think
the order isn't correct, but at
least everything came together, okay?  The
order is wrong, that's not right, it needs to be
changed, it needs to be fixed,
okay?  But well, this is a bit of a
demonstration of what we'll be
working on in the coming days, a moment
to come here, which is the
synchronization between processes and it's
basically when you do
n't need
everyone to come to finish the
operation or when, of course,
finishing the operation depends on everyone having
finished and everyone coming back and everyone
bringing their corresponding piece or not.
Okay, I don't know.  I mean, sometimes it
might be yes and sometimes it might not, it
depends a bit on the context
and little else.  And nothing, and what I hope is
that today,
Luis,
I have given you ideas, but not
evil ideas, okay?  but rather to have
given you ideas in the sense that
I have
always had a lot of affection for this subject.   The thing is, I
've always said it's
a subject that
doesn't have much application in real life because there aren't that
many companies that are looking for
personnel trained in multicore and
multiprocessing, right?  So,
well, I've always said, it's a
subject I love, it's super nice,
but, well, business management systems
is going to give you a lot more
work.  But what's going on?  Well, what I
believe I have told you in
previous classes of this subject, is that
we are in the era of
artificial intelligence, and in the era of
artificial intelligence, distributed
computing
and even parallel computing have a key importance.  And
we have an algorithm on the table
that they might improve in the next few
years, probably, right?  But what about
Transformers?
Curiously, and I'll tell you about it later, it's
terribly parallelizable because
you can take a text and you can put
several heads on that text, each
head does its thing and, obviously, you
can send each head to a
different worker and then in the end
the parts come together.
So, from the point of view
of what I've told you several
times, which is about, well,
winning in Spain, I mean, at a
geographical, local level, gaining
technological independence and not depending so much on other
countries.  Obviously, we should collaborate with other
countries, of course, but we shouldn't
depend so heavily on other
countries, but rather have more
technological independence.  Well, I think
this subject is important,
okay?  And now that's a matter of,
at a given moment, looking for
job offers that fall within this
specific and concrete niche, well, it's
more difficult, obviously, but okay,
but it's something that can be done without any
problem.
Well, that's all for today.  See you
tomorrow, then, for the
first intermodular project and the second
for business management systems.
Tell me, Luis tells, ask.  Wait, I
think you're going to ask me about the
Yes, yes, starting today, but
not today yet, okay?  Which is why I'm
telling you this because I'm closing the topic of
evaluation.  A text editor file
that I had here, a little while,
which will now open with an email that I will
now send to all of you, making
a brief recap, so it's
not yet Exact.  It's still
here, okay?  Hey, you're going to get this one today with the
recap and such,
where I tell you about the evaluation, the
activities, the teaching and all that,
but not the activities yet
, okay?  But since we have
class tomorrow, I'll tell you in more detail
why and what I'm doing,
and I'll show you the Python code
and all that.  Okay?
Come on, see you tomorrow for the
intermodular project and then for
management systems.
Okay, come on, guys, that's it.
Alleluia.